Guide to the George Economou Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
George Economou Papers
1954-1996.
Economou, George.
10 linear ft. (ca. 3,100 items in 15 boxes & 1 map case drawer).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
4078725
This collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, documents, photographs, video and tape recordings, and printed materials relating to Economou's poetry manuscripts, to publications and performances to which he contributed, and to his teaching career as a professor of medieval literature.
Biographical Note
George Demetrios Economou (Columbia University Ph.D., 1967), American poet, critic, medievalist and college teacher, was born in 1934. He is married to Rochelle Owens, poet and playwright.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, photographs, video and tape recordings, and printed materials relating to Economou's poetry manuscripts, to publications and performances to which he contributed, and to his teaching career as a professor of medieval literature. Among the cataloged correspondents are: Paul Blackburn, Robert Creeley, Ted Enslin, Clayton Eshleman, Anselm Hollo, Robert Kelly, Margaret Randall, Charles Tomlinson, and Diane Wakoski.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Correspondence & Manuscripts by other writers
Series II: Writings by Economou
Series III: Tape recordings
Series IV: Photographs
Series V: Printed materiala
Series VI: Oversize materials
Selected materials cataloged; remainder arranged.
Subjects
Antin, David.; Auster, Paul, 1947-; Baraka, Imamu Amiri, 1934-; Blackburn, Paul.; Bly, Robert.; Boas, George, 1891-1980.; Brinnin, John Malcolm, 1916-; Bronk, William.; Chaucer, Geoffrey, d. 1400.; Codrescu, Andrei, 1946-; Congdon, Kirby.; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005.; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321.; Vas Dias, Robert.; Di Prima, Diane.; Dorn, Edward.; Enslin, Theodore.; Eshleman, Clayton.; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Hollo, Anselm.; Hornick, Lita R., 1927-; Kelly, Robert, 1935-; Kostelanetz, Richard.; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997.; Levin, Harry, 1912-1994.; Meltzer, David.; Merwin, W. S. (William Stanley), 1927-; Nicolson, Marjorie Hope, 1894-1981.; Olson, Charles, 1910-1970.; Oppenheimer, Joel.; Owens, Rochelle.; Randall, Margaret, 1936-; Sorrentino, Gilbert.; Tomlinson, Charles, 1927-; Wakoski, Diane.; Waldman, Anne, 1945-; Wieners, John, 1934-2002.; Williams, Jonathan, 1929-2008.; Zukofsky, Louis, 1904-1978.; American literature--20th century.; Greek literature, Modern--20th century.; Literature, Medieval.; Poets, American--20th century.; Poets, Provençal.; Troubadours in literature.; Audio tapes.; Collages.; Interviews.; Manuscripts for publication.; Performances.; Photographs.; Poems.; Posters.; Proofs.; Radio broadcasting.; Scores.; Theses.; Translations.; Videocassettes.; Authors, American.; College teachers.; Critics.; Editors.; Poets.; Medievalists.; Translators.; Women authors, American.; Women dramatists.; Women editors.; Women poets, American.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 3-14. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1974 M-74 Economou, George D.
04/23/1997 M-97-04-23 Papers 6192B Purchase
Gift of George Economou, 1974, 1977, 1982, & 1983.
- Series I: Correspondence & Manuscripts by other writers
  - Subseries I.1: Cataloged correspondence & manuscripts
    - David Antin (Box 1-2)
    - Paul Auster (Box 1-2)
    - Paul Blackburn (Box 1-2)
    - Robert Bly (Box 1-2)
    - George Boas (Box 1-2)
    - John Malcolm Brinnin (Box 1-2)
    - William Bronk (Box 1-2)
    - Andrei Codrescu (Box 1-2)
    - Kirby Congdon (Box 1-2)
    - Robert Creeley (Box 1-2)
    - Robert Vas Dias (Box 1-2)
    - Diane di Prima (Box 1-2)
    - Ed Dorn (Box 1-2)
    - Ted Enslin (Box 1-2)
    - Clayton Eshleman (Box 1-2)
    - Lawrence Ferlinghetti (Box 1-2)
    - Anselm Hollo (Box 1-2)
    - Lita R. Hornick (Box 1-2)
    - LeRoi Jones (Box 1-2)
    - Robert Kelly (Box 1-2)
    - Richard Kostelanetz (Box 1-2)
    - James Laughlin (Box 1-2)
    - Harry Levin (Box 1-2)
    - David Meltzer (Box 1-2)
    - William Stanley Merwin (Box 1-2)
    - Marjorie Hope Nicolson (Box 1-2)
    - Charles Olson (Box 1-2)
    - Joel Oppenheimer (Box 1-2)
    - Rochelle Owens (Box 1-2)
    - Margaret Randall (Box 1-2)
    - Gilbert Sorrentino (Box 1-2)
    - Charles Tomlinson (Box 1-2)
    - Diane Wakoski (Box 1-2)
    - Anne Waldman (Box 1-2)
    - John Wieners (Box 1-2)
    - Jonathan Williams (Box 1-2)
    - Louis Zukofsky (Box 1-2)
  - Subseries I.2:Uncataloged correspondence & manuscripts by others
    - A-G (Box 3)
    - H-O (Box 4)
    - P-Z & Unidentified (Box 5)
- Series II: Writings by Economou
  - Subseries II.1: Poems, essays, & book reviews
    - AMEPIKH (Box 6)
    - [book reviews] (Box 6)
    - Buxó translations (Box 6)
    - Century Dead Center; prose poems (Box 6)
    - The Early Poetry of Rochelle Owens (Box 6)
    - The Elevator Maniac (Box 6)
    - The God-Child (Box 6)
    - Hercules in the Mind (Box 6)
    - Lorca Translations by Paul Blackburn (Box 6)
    - A Note on Rereading Diane Wakoski (Box 6)
    - #15 (ed. By Economou); printed copy with some manuscripts by contributors (Box 6)
    - Philodemus (Box 6)
    - [poems; titled] (Box 7)
    - [poems; untitled] (Box 7)
    - Poems: Summer '78 (Box 7)
    - Some Notes Towards Finding a View of the New Oral Poetry (Box 7)
    - Star (Box 7)
    - Teaching Homer in Honors Composition (Box 7)
    - The Waste-Basket (Box 7)
    - "Whoosh" (Box 7)
    - Misc. manuscripts (Box 7)
    - Misc. documents (Box 7)
    - Notebooks (Box 7)
  - Subseries II.2: Medieval & Renaissance materials
    - Misc. papers & translations (Box 7)
    - Blackburn, Paul: Proensa & other translations, edited by Economou (Box 8)
    - Chaucer (Box 8A)
    - Dante (Box 8A)
    - The Goddess Nature in Medieval Literature (Box 9)
    - Notebooks (Box 9)
    - Piers Plowman (1) (Box 9)
    - Piers Plowman (2): Notebooks & William Langland's Piers Plowman The C Version: a Verse Translation by George Economou (Box 10)
- Series III: Tape recordings
  - Subseries III.1: Reel to Reel
    - Coconut Folksinger by Rochelle Owens, undated (Box 11)
    - "How Much Paint" [by Rochelle Owens] Take 1…, undated (Box 11)
    - [How Much Paint by Rochelle Owens] Video Nugget…, undated (Box 11)
    - I Am the Babe of Joseph Stalin's Daughter. Rochelle Owens, undated (Box 11)
    - A Real Vision: a Documentary on Paul Blackburn's Life and Work, undated (Box 11)
    - WBAI Rochelle Owens. Joe Chronicles: Sacre Coeur, undated (Box 11)
    - Allen Ginsberg reading from unedited journals at the conference, Vancouver, B.C., 1963 August 2 (Box 11)
    - George Economou. Métro, 1965 July 21 (Box 11)
    - "The String Game" [by Rochelle Owens], 1965 February 20 (Box 11)
    - "Istanboul" [by Rochelle Owens], 1965 September 24 (Box 11)
    - Ted Enslin (at L.I.U.), 1965 February 25 (Box 11)
    - Rochelle Owens and Armand Schwerner (at L.I.U.: M. Moore Series), 1965 April 27 (Box 11)
    - Paul Blackburn reading from Probençal at L.I.U.; George Oppen. L.I.U., 1966 February 15 (Box 11)
    - Rochelle Owens at Fischbach Gallery; Jackson MacLow at Fischbach Gallery, 1966 January 13 (Box 11)
    - L.I.U. Read In for Vietnam, 1966 May 11 (Box 11)
    - Schwerner at Fischbach; Blackburn at Fischbach, 1966 May 18 (Box 11)
    - Family tape…, 1972 May 30 (Box 11)
    - Clayton Eshleman [and] Robert Kelly on Paul Blackburn for George Economou & WBAI (3" reel), 1972 February (Box 11)
    - Rochelle Owens at West End, 1974 February 4 (Box 11)
  - Subseries III.2: Tape Cassettes
    - U.C.S.D. Archive for New Poetry. Reading by Rochelle Owens & George Economou, undated (Box 11)
    - Black Box No. 17.[periodical with 2 tape cassettes of readings by Rochelle Owens and others], circa 1979 (Box 11)
    - Dr. George Economou. Poetry Reading. Stillwater [OK], 1986 September 25 (Box 11)
    - Dr. George Economou. Stillwater, OK, 1986 September 25 (Box 11)
  - Subseries III.3: Video Cassette
    - Rochelle Owens/George Economou/ Poetry Reading- O.U. Art Museum, 1987 April 30 (Box 11)
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 12)
- Series V: Printed materials
  - By & about George Economou & misc. (Box 13-14)
- Series VI: Oversize materials
  - Art works: Collage (Box Map case 14-M-06)
  - Photograph of Rochelle Owens (Box Map case 14-M-06)
  - "Portraits and Histories" [texts by George Economou] Music score, tape cassette, & poster (Box Map case 14-M-06)
  - Posters (3) (Box Map case 14-M-06)